SHASHI GOWDA

Office: 32-780, CSAIL, Massachusetts Institute of Technology gowda@mit.edu — +1 (617) 899 4295

With my software engineer hat on, I love to build well-rounded software that is simple, beautiful and fast. With my CS researcher hat on, I think about interpreters, compilers, program synthesis, symbolic computation, machine learning, and the coming together of these fields.

EDUCATION

2018-current

PhD Candidate in Computational Science and Engineering Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA

My thesis project, Symbolics.jl, is the basis for the next generation of programming abstraction in scientific simulation. Combining symbolic programming and partial evaluation, it allows scientists to make a "compiler" for every problem. Right now, 54 other projects with 217 second-degree dependents use Symbolics.jl (source) *Advisor:* Prof. Alan Edelman | The Julia Lab

B. Tech., Information Technology National Institute of Technology, Surathkal, India

2010-2014

EXPERIENCE

2016-2018

Principal Software Engineer, Julia Computing Inc.

Built *JuliaDB*—A distributed-memory analytical database competitive with Spark, pandas (+dask) (more details in our PyData NYC 2017 presentation), and kdb. I built about 80% of the project working at every level, including indexed relational tables (*IndexedTables.jl*), text parser compiler (*TextParse.jl*), compression, distributed blob storage (*MemPool.jl*), parallel scheduling (*Dagger.jl*), distributed table operations and statistics (*JuliaDB.jl*). I also helped clients deploy JuliaDB in machine learning applications and achieve orders of magnitudes of speedups over systems it replaced.

2014-2016

Research Software Engineer, (Remote) CSAIL, MIT

Developed a research distributed-memory array implementation and scheduler (*Dagger.jl*). Also developed DLSs for pedagogical visualizations (*Interact.jl*) and functional-reactive dashboards (*Escher.jl*) which were used in the famous MIT 18.06 and other courses. Leter distilled the core of these into a framework called WebIO, it allows creation of libraries of UI widgets widgets that work in Jupyter, VS Code, and over a standalone web app, without requiring modification.

See shashi.biz for a detailed software portfolio.

PUBLICATIONS

2021

High-performance symbolic-numerics via multiple dispatch

S. Gowda, Y. Ma, A. Cheli, M. Gwóźdź, V.B. Shah, A. Edelman, C. Rackauckas. ACM Communications in Computer Algebra Vol. 55 (dl.acm.org)

2021

ModelingToolkit: A Composable Graph Transformation System For Equation-Based Modeling

Y. Ma, S. Gowda, R. Anantharaman, C. Laughman, V. Shah, C. Rackauckas. preprint arXiv:2103.05244

2019

Sparsity Programming: Automated Sparsity-Aware Optimizations in Differentiable Programming

S. Gowda, Y. Ma, V. Churavy, A. Edelman, C. Rackauckas. NeurIPS Program Transformations for Machine Learning Workshop. (pdf)

	TEACHING EXPERIENCE
Spring 2019 & Fall 2020	Introduction to computational thinking (18.S191)
Fall 2018	High-performance computing (18.337)
	NOTABLE TALKS
2022	Strange Loop, St Louis. "Symbolic-numeric programming in Julia"
2022	SciMLCon, Boston, MA "Symbolic arrays: past, present and future"
2018	JuliaCon, London, UK "How JuliaDB works"
2019	NeurIPS, Workshop on Programming languages for ML, Vancouver BC "Sparsity aware optimizations in differentiable programming"
2017	PyData NYC, NYC "JuliaDB: A data system for Julia (with Jeff Bezanson and Josh Day)"
2016	Microsoft, Bangalore "Keynote: A Functional Algebra of UIs"
2015	JuliaCon, Boston, MA "Escher.jl-a new way to make and deploy UIs"
	September 23, 2023